[
    {
        "question": "Call Number of a Book Means",
        "options": [
            "Book Number",
            "Class Number",
            "Both (A) and (B) are true",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Both (A) and (B) are true"
    },
    {
        "question": "Accession Number means",
        "options": [
            "Call Number of a book",
            "Unique Number for a book inside a particular library.",
            "Book Number",
            "Class number"
        ],
        "answer": "Unique Number for a book inside a particular library."
    },
    {
        "question": "How many digits have in the ISSN",
        "options": [
            "10",
            "8",
            "13",
            "15"
        ],
        "answer": "8"
    },
    {
        "question": "Main use of Shelf list is",
        "options": [
            "Cataloging",
            "Circulation",
            "Stock Verification",
            "Book Selection"
        ],
        "answer": "Stock Verification"
    },
    {
        "question": "Posting the right person at the right place is called ________",
        "options": [
            "Recruitment",
            "Coaching",
            "Deployment",
            "Induction"
        ],
        "answer": "Recruitment"
    },
    {
        "question": "TQM is a system of continuous improvement employing participative management and centered on needs of the ________",
        "options": [
            "Customers",
            "Staff",
            "Organization",
            "Government"
        ],
        "answer": "Organization"
    },
    {
        "question": "Financial support given to libraries are of two types - Recurring and",
        "options": [
            "Ad-hoc",
            "Endowments",
            "Annual",
            "Non-recurring"
        ],
        "answer": "Endowments"
    },
    {
        "question": "Principle of maximum aggregate benefit is concerned with__",
        "options": [
            "Growth of library",
            "Library use",
            "Library service",
            "Library fee"
        ],
        "answer": "Library service"
    },
    {
        "question": "\u2026\u2026.. takes items of expenditure for libraries as the working data for allocation of funds.",
        "options": [
            "Method of details",
            "Per capita method",
            "Principle of economy",
            "Library budget"
        ],
        "answer": "Library budget"
    },
    {
        "question": "A budget which mainly covers items of current revenue and expenditure is called __.",
        "options": [
            "Programme budget",
            "Welfare economics",
            "Current budgeting",
            "Capital budgeting"
        ],
        "answer": "Capital budgeting"
    },
    {
        "question": "The library budget of a university is passed by the ?",
        "options": [
            "Senate",
            "Executive Council",
            "Academic Council",
            "Research Council"
        ],
        "answer": "Executive Council"
    },
    {
        "question": "In fund accounting _______ fund can not be used for other purposes.",
        "options": [
            "Recurring",
            "Non-recurring",
            "Restricted",
            "Encumbering"
        ],
        "answer": "Recurring"
    },
    {
        "question": "Scrutiny of financial transactions is called",
        "options": [
            "Budgeting",
            "Programming",
            "Accounting",
            "Auditing"
        ],
        "answer": "Auditing"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the two parts of the annual report of the library",
        "options": [
            "Primary and Secondary",
            "Analytical and Systematic",
            "Upper and Lower",
            "Descriptive and Statistical"
        ],
        "answer": "Descriptive and Statistical"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many columns are there in the accession register?",
        "options": [
            "10",
            "12",
            "14",
            "16"
        ],
        "answer": "14"
    },
    {
        "question": "PPBS relates to",
        "options": [
            "Book selection",
            "Journal selection",
            "Budgeting",
            "Library records"
        ],
        "answer": "Budgeting"
    },
    {
        "question": "Zero based budget is concerned with",
        "options": [
            "Present",
            "Past",
            "Future",
            "Remote future"
        ],
        "answer": "Future"
    },
    {
        "question": "Another term of PERT is",
        "options": [
            "CPM",
            "POSDCORB",
            "MBO",
            "HRM"
        ],
        "answer": "CPM"
    },
    {
        "question": "POSDCORB is related to",
        "options": [
            "Library cataloguing",
            "Library reference service",
            "Library administration",
            "Library automation"
        ],
        "answer": "Library administration"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the standard size of the Accession Register is",
        "options": [
            "16\u201d * 12\u201d",
            "16\u201d * 13\u201d",
            "16\u201d * 11\u201d",
            "16\u201d * 18\u201d"
        ],
        "answer": "16\u201d * 13\u201d"
    },
    {
        "question": "A good library building is an outcome of librarian and.",
        "options": [
            "Registrar",
            "Building Corporation",
            "Finance Officer",
            "Architect"
        ],
        "answer": "Architect"
    },
    {
        "question": "________ are the storage areas for the various types of documents kept in a library.",
        "options": [
            "Tasks .",
            "Racks",
            "Stacks",
            "Desks"
        ],
        "answer": "Stacks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Study carrels are exclusive areas meant for",
        "options": [
            "Students",
            "Public",
            "Women",
            "Researchers"
        ],
        "answer": "Researchers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Library catalogue cards are filed in specially designed drawers called",
        "options": [
            "Charging tray",
            "Catalogue cabinet",
            "Display rack .",
            "Filling equipment"
        ],
        "answer": "Catalogue cabinet"
    },
    {
        "question": "Information Gatekeepers come under ________ sources.",
        "options": [
            "Documentary",
            "Human",
            "Institutional",
            "Neo-conventional"
        ],
        "answer": "Documentary"
    },
    {
        "question": "________ is a legal document and can be used as a source of industrial information.",
        "options": [
            "Report",
            "Law Review",
            "Patent",
            "Specification"
        ],
        "answer": "Specification"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Encyclopaedia Britianica ___________ acts as an index to macropaedia.",
        "options": [
            "Bibliography",
            "Introduction Part",
            "Propaedia",
            "Micropaedia"
        ],
        "answer": "Micropaedia"
    },
    {
        "question": "One of the book selection principles states that \u201cthe best reading for the largest number at the \u2026\u2026\u2026\u2026\u2026Cost.\u201d",
        "options": [
            "Maximum",
            "Medium",
            "Least",
            "Zero"
        ],
        "answer": "Least"
    },
    {
        "question": "Payments for the books purchased can be made only after",
        "options": [
            "Accessioning",
            "Classification",
            "ataloguing",
            "Arrangement in the shelve"
        ],
        "answer": "Accessioning"
    },
    {
        "question": "The standard size of an accession register is ?",
        "options": [
            "15\u201d x 13\u201d",
            "16 x 13\u201d",
            "2\u201d x 5\u201d",
            "5\u201d x 3\u201d"
        ],
        "answer": "16 x 13\u201d"
    },
    {
        "question": "Technical section performs mainly two functions namely classification and",
        "options": [
            "Accessioning",
            "Bills payment",
            "Cataloguing",
            "Shelving"
        ],
        "answer": "Cataloguing"
    },
    {
        "question": "Getting books back from the users and releasing the borrower\u2019s ticket is known as",
        "options": [
            "Charging",
            "Holding",
            "Reserving",
            "Discharging"
        ],
        "answer": "Discharging"
    },
    {
        "question": "While entering the library the personal belongings of a reader is kept in ________",
        "options": [
            "Cloak Room",
            "Property Counter",
            "Gate counter",
            "Store room"
        ],
        "answer": "Property Counter"
    },
    {
        "question": "Books misplaced on the shelves by readers are restored. This work is referred to as.",
        "options": [
            "Shelving",
            "Stock verification",
            "Shelf rectification",
            "Shifting"
        ],
        "answer": "Shelf rectification"
    },
    {
        "question": "Outdated and seldom used books are withdrawn from the library is known as ___________.",
        "options": [
            "Shelving",
            "Weeding",
            "Circulating",
            "Guiding"
        ],
        "answer": "Weeding"
    },
    {
        "question": "The objective of library binding is ________of the library materials.",
        "options": [
            "Proper organisation",
            "Accessibility.",
            "Durability",
            "Humidity control"
        ],
        "answer": "Durability"
    },
    {
        "question": "All part and pages of a volume are correctly sequenced in the first stage of binding process known as?",
        "options": [
            "Sewing",
            "Guard",
            "Pulling",
            "Collation"
        ],
        "answer": "Collation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Sheets before and after the text of a book are called _________. .",
        "options": [
            "End papers",
            "Attach cover",
            "Head bands",
            "Gilding"
        ],
        "answer": "End papers"
    },
    {
        "question": "Leather being used as one of the binding materials i.e. _________ is the strongest leather.",
        "options": [
            "Roan",
            "Imitation",
            "Pig skin",
            "Sheep skin"
        ],
        "answer": "Sheep skin"
    },
    {
        "question": "________ has prescribed certain standards for library binding.",
        "options": [
            "ILA",
            "ALA",
            "BLA",
            "NBT"
        ],
        "answer": "ALA"
    },
    {
        "question": "A skillful method of providing means mechanism and structural elements to. streamline organizational work is known as _______",
        "options": [
            "Strategic planning",
            "Role analysis",
            "Work culture",
            "Autonomous planning"
        ],
        "answer": "Strategic planning"
    },
    {
        "question": "Calcutta Public Library was established during",
        "options": [
            "15th Century",
            "16th Century",
            "19th Century",
            "20th Century."
        ],
        "answer": "19th Century"
    },
    {
        "question": "______ budgeting does not take into account what happened in the past but emphasizes on current activities.",
        "options": [
            "Formula",
            "Performance",
            "Programme",
            "Zero-base"
        ],
        "answer": "Performance"
    },
    {
        "question": "The library budget of a university is passed by the?",
        "options": [
            "Senate",
            "Executive Council",
            "Academic Council",
            "Research Council"
        ],
        "answer": "Executive Council"
    },
    {
        "question": "In fund accounting _______ fund cannot be used for other purposes.",
        "options": [
            "Recurring",
            "Non-recurring",
            "Restricted",
            "Encumbering"
        ],
        "answer": "Recurring"
    },
    {
        "question": "Scrutiny of financial transactions is called",
        "options": [
            "Budgeting",
            "Programming",
            "Accounting",
            "Auditing"
        ],
        "answer": "Auditing"
    },
    {
        "question": "________ is one of the records of circulation section.",
        "options": [
            "Accession Register",
            "Day book",
            "Catalogue Card",
            "AACR-2 (R)"
        ],
        "answer": "Accession Register"
    },
    {
        "question": "The marketing concepts in Library Service include",
        "options": [
            "analysis planning implementation and control",
            "advertising planning analysis and control",
            "distribution control analysis implementation",
            "indexing planning control and implementation."
        ],
        "answer": "advertising planning analysis and control"
    },
    {
        "question": "There are a few basic factors which may be applied in winning the hearts of the readers. They are",
        "options": [
            "Psychological factor environmental factor social factor",
            "Self factor psychological factor service factor",
            "Service factor philosophical factor self factor",
            "Technological factor service factor self factor."
        ],
        "answer": "Technological factor service factor self factor."
    }
]